ABOLFAZL HASHEMI

Office: MSEE 344, 501 Northwestern Ave., West Lafayette, Indiana 47907-2035

Phone: (765) 496-6040 \$\display \text{Email: abolfazl@purdue.edu}\$ \$\display \text{Website: https://abolfazlh.github.io}\$

CURRENT POSITION

Assistant Professor

Purdue University

August 2021 – present

Elmore Family School of Electrical and Computer Engineering

RESEARCH DESCRIPTION

My research interests include the study of Machine Learning, Online Learning, Learning in Games, and Networked/Distributed Decision-Making from the perspective of optimization. In doing so, we design efficient algorithms with mathematical guarantees to render practical deployment of learning-based systems possible under a variety of considerations such as limited resources, and robustness, and adversarial behaviors.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.) , Electrical and Computer Engineering University of Texas at Austin, Austin, Texas, USA	2016 - 2020
Master of Science in Engineering (M.S.E.), Electrical and Computer Engineering University of Texas at Austin, Austin, Texas, USA	2014 - 2016
Bachelor of Science (B.S.), Electrical Engineering Sharif University of Technology, Tehran, Iran	2010 - 2014

PREVIOUS POSITIONS

Postdoctoral Fellow	
University of Texas at Austin	2020-2021

Oden Institute for Computational Engineering and Sciences

Advisors: Prof. Rachel Ward, Prof. Inderjit Dhillon, Prof. Ufuk Topcu

Graduate Research and Teaching Assistant

University of Texas at Austin	2014 - 2020
-------------------------------	-------------

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering

Advisor: Prof. Haris Vikalo

Data Scientist Intern

Cognitive Scale, Austin, Texas	Summer 2017
--------------------------------	-------------

Undergraduate Research Intern

Hong Kong University of Science and Technology	Summer 2013
nong Kong University of Science and Technology	Summer 2013

Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering

Host: Prof. Daniel Palomar

Undergraduate Research and Teaching Assistant

Sharif Universit	y of Technology 201	12 - 2014

Department of Electrical Engineering

INVITED PRESENTATIONS

1. Theory-guided Methods for Private Federated Learning, SIAM Conference on Computational Science and Engineering, March 2023.

- 2. No-Regret Learning in Dynamic Stackelberg Games, Information Theory and Applications Workshop, Feb. 2023.
- 3. Generalization Bounds for Sparse Random Feature Expansions, SIAM Conference on Mathematics and Data Science (MDS), September 2022.
- 4. Faster Non-Convex Federated Learning via Global and Local Momentum, 2022 NSF TRIPODS PI Meeting, September 2022.
- 5. On the Convergence of Differentially Private Federated Learning on Non-Lipschitz Objectives via Clipping and Normalized Client Updates, Federated Learning One World Seminar, April 2022.
- 6. AI at Scale: Robustness and Security in Adversarial Environments, The Center for Education and Research in Information Assurance and Security (CERIAS), Purdue University, Oct. 2021.
- 7. Structured and Resource-Constrained Collaborative Learning, Center for Innovation in Control, Optimization, and Networks (ICON), Purdue University, Sep. 2021.
- 8. Structured and Resource-Constrained Collaborative Learning, Department of Computer Science, Purdue University, Sep. 2021.
- 9. Weak Submodular Optimization: Theory, Algorithm, Application, Department of Computer Science at UIUC, Feb. 2020.
- 10. Progressive Stochastic Greedy Sparse Reconstruction and Support Selection, 15th CSL student conference at UIUC, Feb. 2020.
- 11. Tutorial on Submodular Maximization, The Oden Institute for Computational Engineering and Sciences at UT Austin, Nov. 2019.
- 12. Tutorial on Submodular Minimization, The Oden Institute for Computational Engineering and Sciences at UT Austin, Oct. 2019.
- 13. Sparse Tensor Decomposition for Haplotype Assembly of Diploids and Polyploids, 12th CSL student conference at UIUC, Feb. 2017.

PUBLICATIONS

Journal Papers

- 1. Lauffer, N., Ghasemi, M., Hashemi, A., Savas, Y., Topcu, U., "No-Regret Learning in Dynamic Stackelberg Games," IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control, 2023.
- 2. Chellapandi, V., Upadhyay, A., Hashemi, A., Zak, S., "On the Convergence of Decentralized Federated Learning Under Imperfect Information Sharing," IEEE Control Systems Letters, 2023.
- 3. Upadhyay, A., Hashemi, A., "Improved Convergence Analysis and SNR Control Strategies for Federated Learning in the Presence of Noise," **IEEE Access**, 2023.
- 4. Kaya, E., Sahin, M., Hashemi, A., "Communication-Efficient Zeroth-Order Distributed Online Optimization: Algorithm, Theory, and Applications," IEEE Access, 2023.
- 5. Hashemi*, A., Schaeffer*, H., Shi*, B., Tran*, G., Ward*, R., "Generalization Bounds for Sparse Random Feature Expansions," Applied and Computational Harmonic Analysis, 2022.
- 6. Hashemi, A., Vikalo, H., de Veciana, G., "On the Benefits of Progressively Increasing Sampling Sizes in Stochastic Greedy Weak Submodular Maximization," IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing, 2022.
- 7. Ghasemi, M., Hashemi, A., Vikalo, H., Topcu, U., "Learning in Markov Decision Processes with Varying Rewards: High Probability Regret Bounds under Bandit Feedback and Unknown Horizon," IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control (conditionally accepted), 2022.

- 8. Hashemi, A., Shafipour, R., Vikalo, H., Mateos, G., "Towards Accelerated Greedy Sampling and Reconstruction of Bandlimited Graph Signals," Signal Processing, 2022.
- 9. Hashemi, A., Acharya*, A., Das*, R., Vikalo, H., Sanghavi, S., Dhillon, I., "On the Benefits of Multiple Gossip Steps in Communication-Constrained Decentralized Federated Learning," IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems, Special Section on Parallel and Distributed Computing Techniques for AI, ML, and DL, 2022.
- 10. Chen, Y., Hashemi, A., Vikalo, H., "Communication-Efficient Variance-Reduced Decentralized Stochastic Optimization over Time-Varying Directed Graphs," IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control, 2022.
- 11. Hashemi, A., Ghasemi, M., Vikalo, H., Topcu, U., "Randomized Greedy Sensor Selection: Leveraging Weak Submodularity," IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control, Jan. 2021.
- 12. Hashemi, A. and Vikalo, H., "Evolutionary Self-Expressive Models for Subspace Clustering," **IEEE Journal of Selected Topics in Signal Processing, Special Issue on Data Science: Robust Subspace Learning and Tracking,** vol. 12, no. 6, pp. 1534–1546, Dec. 2018.
- 13. Hashemi, A. and Vikalo, H., "Accelerated Orthogonal Least-Squares for Large-Scale Sparse Reconstruction," Digital Signal Processing, vol. 82, pp. 91–105, Nov. 2018.
- 14. Hashemi, A., Zhu, B., Vikalo, H., "Sparse Tensor Decomposition for Haplotype Assembly of Diploids and Polyploids," BMC Genomics, vol. 19, no. 4, pp. 1–15, Mar. 2018.

Conference Papers

- 1. Kaya*, E., Sahin*, M., Hashemi, A., "Communication-Constrained Exchange of Zeroth-Order Information with Application to Collaborative Target Tracking," International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2023.
- 2. Chen, Y., Hashemi, A., Vikalo, H., "Accelerated Decentralized Stochastic Non-Convex Optimization over Directed Networks," International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2023.
- 3. Hibbard, M., Hashemi, A., Tanaka, T., Topcu, U., "Randomized Greedy Algorithms for Sensor Selection in Large-Scale Satellite Constellations," American Control Conference, 2023.
- 4. Das, R., Hashemi, A., Sanghavi, S., Dhillon, I., "DP-NormFedAvg: Normalizing Client Updates for Privacy-Preserving Federated Learning," 14th International Workshop on Optimization for Machine Learning at NeurIPS, 2022.
- 5. Das, R., Hashemi*, A., Acharya*, A., Sanghavi, S., Dhillon, I., Topcu, U., "Faster Non-Convex Federated Learning via Global and Local Momentum," Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence (UAI), 2022.
- 6. Acharya, A., Hashemi, A., Jain, P., Sanghavi, S., Dhillon, I., Topcu, U., "Robust SGD via Block coordinate Geometric Median Descent," International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), 2022.
- 7. Ghasemi*, M., Hashemi*, A., Vikalo, H., Topcu, U., "No-Regret Learning with High-Probability in Adversarial Markov Decision Processes," Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence (UAI), 2021.
- 8. Ghasemi, M., Hashemi, A., Topcu, U., Vikalo, H., "Online Learning with Implicit Exploration in Episodic Markov Decision Processes," American Control Conference (ACC), 2021.
- 9. Savas, Y., Hashemi, A., Vinod, AP., Sadler, BM., Topcu, U., "Physical-Layer Security via Distributed Beam-forming in the Presence of Adversaries with Unknown Locations," International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2021.

- 10. Chen, Y., Hashemi, A., Vikalo, H., "Decentralized Optimization on Time-Varying Directed Graphs under Communication Constraints," International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2021.
- 11. Hashemi, A., Vikalo, H., de Veciana, G., "On the Performance-Complexity Tradeoff in Stochastic Greedy Weak Submodular Optimization," International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2021.
- 12. Ghasemi, M., Hashemi, A., Vikalo, H., Topcu, U., "Identifying Low-Dimensional Structures in Markov Chains: A Nonnegative Matrix Factorization Approach," American Control Conference (ACC), 2020.
- 13. Ghasemi*, M., Hashemi*, A., Vikalo, H., Topcu, U., "On Submodularity of Quadratic Observation Selection in Constrained Networked Sensing Systems," American Control Conference (ACC), 2019.
- 14. Shafipour, R., Hashemi, A., Mateos, G., Vikalo, H., "Online Topology Inference from Streaming Stationary Graph Signals," Data Science Workshop (DSW), 2019.
- 15. Hashemi, A., Ghasemi, M., Vikalo, H., Topcu, U., "Submodular Observation Selection and Information Gathering for Quadratic Models," International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), June 2019.
- 16. Hashemi, A. and Vikalo, H., "Evolutionary Subspace Clustering: Discovering Structure In Self-expressive Time-series Data," International Conference on Acoustic, Speech and Signal Processing, 2019.
- 17. Consul, S., Hashemi, A., Vikalo, H., "A MAP Framework for Support Recovery of Sparse Signals Using Orthogonal Least Squares," International Conference on Acoustic, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), Brighton, 2019.
- 18. Hashemi*, A., Kilic*, O.F., Vikalo, H., "Near-Optimal Distributed Estimation for a Network of Sensing Units Operating Under Communication Constraints," Conference on Decision and Control (CDC), 2018.
- 19. Hashemi, A., Shafipour, R., Vikalo, H., Mateos, G., "A Novel Scheme for Support Identification and Iterative Sampling of Bandlimited Graph Signals," Global Conference on Signal and Information Processing (GlobalSIP), 2018.
- 20. Hashemi, A., Ghasemi, M., Vikalo, H., Topcu, U., "A Randomized Greedy Algorithm for Near-Optimal Sensor Scheduling in Large-Scale Sensor Networks," American Control Conference (ACC), 2018. (Best student paper award finalist)
- 21. Hashemi, A., Shafipour, R., Vikalo, H., Mateos, G., "Sampling and Reconstruction of Graph Signals via Weak Submodularity and Semidefinite Relaxation," International Conference on Acoustic, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2018.
- 22. Hashemi, A., Zhu, B., Vikalo, H., "Sparse Tensor Decomposition for Haplotype Assembly of Diploids and Polyploids," International Workshop on Computational Network Biology: Modeling, Analysis, Control (CNB-MAC), 2017.
- 23. Hashemi, A. and Vikalo, H., "Sparse Recovery via Branch and Bound Least-Squares," International Conference on Acoustic, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2017.
- 24. Hashemi, A. and Vikalo, H., "Sparse Linear Regression via Generalized Orthogonal Least-Squares," Global Conference on Signal and Information Processing (GlobalSIP), 2016.

SCHOLASTIC HONORS

- Outstanding Reviewer of ICML 2020, August 2020
- 1 of 4 selected as an invited student speaker at 15th CSL conference at UIUC, Machine Learning for Signal Processing session, February 2020

- Selected as the Schmidt Science Fellows Award nominee from UT Austin, 2019
- Best student paper award finalist, American Control Conference, June 2018
- 1 of 4 selected as an invited student speaker at 12th CSL conference at UIUC, Bioinformatics and Computational Genomics session, February 2017
- Travel awards for ICML 2019, ACC 2019, ACC 2018, CNB-MAC 2017, ICASSP 2017, GlobalSIP 2016
- Inclusive Classrooms Leadership Certificate, UT Austin, February 2015
- Professional Teaching Assistant Certificate, UT Austin, August 2014
- Qualied as an Exceptional Talent eligible to enter Graduate Studies without entrance exam, Sharif University of Technology, 2013
- Ranked 79th among more than 277,000 participants in the Nationwide University Entrance Exam for B.Sc. degree, 2010
- Recipient of Iranian National Elite Foundation fellowship, 2010-2014

TE

• Communication Systems

• Principles of Electronics

• Principles of Electronics

• Computer Architecture

EACHING EXPERIENCE	
Purdue University Elmore Family School of Electrical and Computer Engineering Instructor	
• ECE 69500: Optimization for Deep Learning	Fall 2023
• Vertically Integrated Projects (VIP), Team RoboMaster	Spring 2023
• ECE 20001: Electrical Engineering Fundamental I	Spring 2023
• ECE 69500: Optimization for Deep Learning	Fall 2022
• Vertically Integrated Projects (VIP), Team RoboMaster	Fall 2022
• ECE 20001: Electrical Engineering Fundamental I	Spring 2022
• ECE 20001: Electrical Engineering Fundamental I	Fall 2021
University of Texas at Austin Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering Graduate Teaching Assistant	
• Statistical Machine Learning	Fall 2019
• Estimation Theory	Fall 2017
• Digital Signal Processing	Spring 2015
• Digital Signal Processing	Fall 2014
Sharif University of Technology Department of Electrical Engineering Undergraduate Teaching Assistant	
• Digital Signal Processing	Fall 2013

Fall 2013

Fall 2013

Spring 2013

Spring 2013

• Logic Circuits Spring 2013

• Analog Circuits Spring 2013

• Electromagnetism Fall 2012

ADVISING

Current Ph.D. Students

- Antesh Upadhyay (since December 2021)
- Ege Kaya (since August 2022)
- Andres C Castillo (since August 2022)
- Mehmet Berk Sahin (since August 2022), Co-adviser: Prof. Behzad Sharif
- Sang Bin Moon (since August 2022), Co-adviser: Prof. Jan-Anders Mansson
- Dilek Yalcinkaya (since August 2022), Co-advised with Prof. Behzad Sharif

Current M.Sc. Students with Thesis

• Sravani Ramishetty (since December 2021)

Other Advising Roles

- Actively advising undergraduates through programs such as SURF and Summer Stay
- Serving on the committee of eight PhD. students.
- Faculty advisor for Purdue RoboMaster Club, Plurimos LLP, and ECE COMPES.

SERVICES AT THE PURDUE UNIVERSITY

• Member of the SMI committee for PMP students

October 2022 – present

• Member of the graduate admissions committee, CNSIP and CE areas December 2021 – present

• Co-organizer of ICON Seminar Series Spring 2022

• Co-organizer of two ECE Seminars Fall 2022

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS AND SERVICES

Grant Proposal Panels

• NSF Panelist, 2023

Conference/Workshop Organizer

- Panelist in TRIPODS Postdoc Workshop, Toyota Technological Institute at Chicago August, 2023
- EnCORE Institute Sessions on "Distributed Learning and Decision-Making" at ITA 2023

Technical Program Committees

• Networks and Communication Systems Technical Committee IEEE Control Systems Society

October 2022 – present

2023

Area Chair

• 26th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS) 2023

• International Conference on Images, Signals, and Computing (ICISC)

• International Workshop on Signal Processing Advances in Wireless Communications (SPAWC) 2020

• International Multi-Conference on Computing in the Global Information Technology	2019
• International Conference on Mobile, Hybrid, and Online Learning	2019
• International Conference on Advanced Engineering Computing and Applications in Sciences	2018
\bullet International Multi-Conference on Computing in the Global Information Technology	2018

Memberships

• Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE), Signal Processing Society 2016 – present

• Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics (SIAM)

2016 – present

Journal Reviews

- IEEE Control Systems Letters
- IEEE Signal Processing Magazine
- IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing
- IEEE Signal Processing Letters
- IEEE Transactions on Signal and Information Processing over Networks
- Elsevier Signal Processing
- IET Signal Processing
- IEEE Transactions on Robotics
- IEEE Transactions on Control of Networked Systems
- IEEE Transactions on Automatic Control
- Automatica
- IEEE Transactions on Wireless Communications
- IEEE Transactions on Communications
- IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics
- IEEE Journal of Selected Areas in Information Theory
- IEEE Access
- Information Sciences
- SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing
- Nature Scientific Reports
- PLOS One
- Taylor and Francis Journal on Forensic Sciences Research

• International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)

Conference Reviews

• International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP) 2023

• International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS)

2020, 2021, 2022, 2023

• Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)

2020, 2022

2021

• American Control Conference (ACC)

2020, 2021, 2022

• International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)

2020

2020

• International Workshop on Signal Processing Advances in Wireless Communications (SPAWC)

• Conference on Decision and Control (CDC)

2018,2023

• International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP)

2022, 2023

SHORT BIO

Abolfazl Hashemi received the B.Sc. degree in Electrical Engineering from the Sharif University of Technology, Iran, in July 2014, and the M.S.E. and Ph.D. degrees in Electrical and Computer Engineering from the University of Texas at Austin, USA, in May 2016 and August 2020, respectively. From August 2020 to August 2021 he was a Postdoctoral Scholar at the Oden Institute for Computational Engineering and Sciences at the University of Texas at Austin. Since August 2021, he has been an Assistant Professor at the Elmore Family School of Electrical and Computer Engineering at Purdue University. Abolfazl was the 2019 Schmidt Science Fellows Award nominee from UT Austin, and the recipient of the Iranian national elite foundation fellowship and a best student paper award finalist at the 2018 American Control Conference. His research interests include optimization for machine learning, signal processing, and control.

Last Update: 20^{th} Jun, 2023